HIRAYAMA TOFU SHOP
（平山豆腐店）
GANMODOKI
（炸豆腐餅）
I saw Santa Claus.
我看到聖誕老人了
Where?
在哪裡？
Seriously?
真的假的？
In a dream.
在夢裡
Oh, a dream.
夢裡啊
And?
然後呢？
He asked me, "Is there anything you want?"
他問我“妳想要什麼？”
And what did you ask for?
那妳想要什麼？
Well…
這個嘛…
At the time, I couldn't think of what I wanted, so…
當時我想不到自己要什麼
Never mind me.
不用管我
SHUJI KIRITANI
（桐谷修二）
Go and ask Shuji Kiritani.
你去問桐谷修二吧
I saw him in a dream too!
我也有夢到他
-Really? -Yes.
-真的嗎？ -對
-You liar. -No! I mean it!
-你這個騙子 -不，我是說真的
Yes, I saw him and he asked me too.
我看到他，他也問了我
"Is there anything you want?"
“你想要什麼？”
No. Forget about me.
不用管我
Why don't you ask Kusano?
你去問草野吧？
-Me? -Yes.
-我？ -對
Did you see Santa Claus?
你見到聖誕老人了嗎？
You liars!
你們這些騙子
Both of you. There's no way that happened…
你們兩個都是騙子，怎麼可能…
-Yes, it did. -You saw him?
-有 -見到了吧？
-Right? -Yes.
-對吧？ -見到了
What did Santa Claus say?
聖誕老人說了什麼？
Well…
這個嘛…
Something like, "I'll give you a present!"
好像是“我會送你一個禮物”
What do I want? Well…
我想要什麼？這個嘛…
Curry buns.
咖哩麵包
That's what I said.
我是這麼說的
Curry buns?
咖哩麵包？
These were gifts. Help yourselves.
這些是禮物，你們吃吧
-Wow! -Thank you.
-天啊 -謝謝
-It's Santa! -Whoa!
-是聖誕老人 -天啊
I was forced to wear this and work the lottery booth in the shopping arcade.
我被迫穿上這套服裝 在商店街裡賣彩券
Okay, be good boys and girls. Merry Christmas!
你們要乖啊，聖誕快樂
Santa came.
是聖誕老人
-Shuji. -Yes?
-修二 -什麼？
Curry buns!
咖哩麵包
Santa Claus granted your wish.
聖誕老人真的實現了你的願望
He sure did.
對啊
Why the heck did you sever our loop of goodwill?
你為什麼要切斷我們的善意循環？
And of all things, you asked for curry buns?
而且偏偏要選咖哩麵包？
He didn't tell me you referred him to me!
他又沒說是你介紹過來的
If you'd told him to go see Nobuta,
如果你叫他去找野豬
the loop of goodwill would have been complete.
善意循環就完整了
You opted for curry buns instead.
你卻選了咖哩麵包
It was going so well, then you asked for curry buns.
本來很順利，你卻選擇咖哩麵包
-That does suck. -Yes, it's appalling.
-真的很差勁 -太過分了
It's appalling!
太過分了
I'm leaving.
我要走了
-I'm leaving too. -How come?
-我也要走了 -為什麼？
But the chime hasn't rung.
但鐘聲還沒響呢
Hey, come on. The chime still hasn't rung.
喂，等一下，鐘聲還沒響啊
What?
什麼？
That was all just a dream!
那只是一個夢啊
Grow up, would you?
成熟一點，好嗎？
You think we were a little cruel?
我們會不會有點殘忍？
No, he'll be fine.
他不會有事的
He'll be just fine.
沒事的…
I don't want to move.
我不想搬家
We just have to accept it.
這有什麼辦法
It's Dad's work, after all.
畢竟是爸爸的工作
And I loved this place too.
我也很喜歡這裡
Actually…
其實呢
Wait a minute.
等一下
I think I can smile now!
我現在會笑了
It needs a little more work.
還需要再練習一下
Oh…
這樣啊…
You're almost there.
就快成功了
Oh, what was it?
是什麼來著？
What was it? I forgot.
是什麼？我忘了
I forgot.
我忘了
I couldn't say that I was moving away.
我說不出口自己要搬家了
I'll tell them today. I swear I'll tell them.
我今天會跟他們說，我絕對要說
-Say… -Hey…
-聽我說
There's something I want to say.
我有話想跟你們說
How come…
為什麼…
you never call me by my name?
你們從沒叫過我的名字？
What? We don't?
什麼？沒有嗎？
What did we call you?
那我們叫你什麼？
You say "Hey" or "You."
你們都說“喂”或“等等”
I call you guys "Shuji" and "Nobuta."
但我都叫你們“修二”和“野豬”
But you don't call me anything.
你們卻從不叫我的名字
Don't be stupid. We do use your name.
別傻了，我們有叫你的名字啊
We call you "Kusano."
我們都叫你草野啊
-"Kusano." -That sounds so distant.
-草野 -聽起來好有距離感
Then what do you want us to call you?
那你希望我們怎麼稱呼你？
"Hey…"
“聽我說
"Oh, Akira!"
彰
"Yip!"
嗷”
Call me by my first name.
叫我的名字就好
What is your first name?
你叫什麼名字？
Akira is shocked!
彰心碎滿地
You don't know?
你不知道？
What?
什麼？
Akira!
彰
Oh, right.
對啦…
Are you angry?
妳生氣了嗎？
-Like that? -She's not angry.
-像這樣嗎？ -她沒有生氣
Say it again.
再說一次
Try saying it a little more tenderly.
試著再溫柔一點
Nobuta!
野豬
I don't want us to become any closer than this.
我不想跟你們變得更要好
Try saying my name.
試試看叫我的名字
Shuji.
修二
That's so kind.
真溫柔
Now try saying, "Shuji and Akira."
現在說“修二與彰”
Shuji and Akira!
修二與彰
Who am I to you?
我對妳來說究竟是誰？
Try "Shuji and Akira…"
試著說“修二與彰”
We'll be splitting up soon.
我們很快就會分開了
So becoming closer…
感情越好…
Akira!
彰
…would just make it sadder.
只會更悲傷
Now for my final question.
最後一個問題
Are you two in love?
你們相愛嗎？
Yes, we are.
很相愛喔
How's Chie's cooking?
知惠的廚藝如何？
It's still yucky.
還是很難吃
That's it for the Sumidagawa High Lunchtime broadcast.
以上是隅田川高中的午間廣播
Cut!
卡
Thank you very much, everyone.
非常感謝各位
Kotani!
-小谷學姊
Won't you please take a photo with us?
可以跟我們…
-That's a great idea! -Take one with us too!
-好主意 -我們來幫妳們拍吧
-Destiny?
-命運
-How cute! -Nice!
-好可愛 -好讚
Kotani!
-小谷
Hang in there!
-加油喔
Give me your autograph!
幫我簽名
They want her autograph!
他們想要她的簽名
Wow! She's famous now.
她變成名人了
-Yes. -Kotani's pretty amazing.
-對啊 -小谷真厲害
Yes.
對啊
AKIRA KUSANO
（草野彰）
-Say…
-聽我說…
What? What is it?
什麼？怎麼了？
Oh, never mind me. It's not a big deal.
別管我，沒什麼大不了的
Then you go, Nobuta.
那妳說吧，野豬
I… Actually…
其實我…
I'm not sure how to say this.
我不知道該怎麼說
After everything you two have done for me, I'm not sure I should say this.
你們為我做了那麼多 我不知道該不該說
It's actually really brutal doing the "Surprise Lunch Check."
其實做“午餐突襲”很殘忍
I see.
這樣啊
-Then quit doing it. -But…
-那就不要做啊 -但是…
-I can? -Yes. You don't like it, right?
-可以嗎？ -對啊，妳不是不想做嗎？
But unless I put up with this kind of thing, I won't become popular, right?
但我要忍受做下去 才會有人氣，對吧？
Well,
這個嘛…
to be honest, I don't understand why being popular is such a good thing.
老實說，我完全不理解 人氣高有什麼好的
But
但是…
didn't we say that we'd make Nobuta popular?
我們不是答應過 要讓野豬擁有高人氣嗎？
Akira!
彰
What did you want to say?
你剛剛想說什麼？
Like I said, forget about me. It's not a big deal.
就像我說的，別管我 沒什麼大不了的
Not at all.
完全不重要
Tell us. I want to know now.
告訴我們吧，我想知道
No. I mean it.
不，我是說真的
Let's not. I take it back.
不說了，我收回
This kind of thing shouldn't be said.
這種事不能說
Akira!
彰
No!
不說
Fine, I'll say it.
那我就說吧
What's that?
那是什麼？
Inside here is something that I want to forget.
這裡面有我想忘記的東西
AKIRA KUSANO
（草野彰）
That stinks! What is that?
好臭，那是什麼？
What is that?
那是什麼？
A biology test. Twenty-eight out of 100.
生物考試，28分
What? You wanted to forget that?
什麼？你想忘記這件事嗎？
That's not it.
不是那件事
What?
什麼？
It's gone!
不見了
It's gone. So tell us your thing now.
不見了，那把你想說的話告訴我們吧
What's with that?
這是在搞什麼啊？
Actually…
其實呢
In the new year…
明年…
I'll be moving.
我就要搬家了
After this semester,
等這個學期結束
I'll be leaving
我就要離開
this school.
這間學校了
You mean, the decision
你是說…
is final?
這事已經確定了嗎？
Yes.
對
Nobuta!
野豬
Don't you have to go after Nobuta?
你不去追野豬嗎？
You're seriously moving away?
你真的要搬走了嗎？
Yes.
對
This stinks.
好臭
He knew?
原來他知道？
You must be cold.
妳一定很冷
Here.
給妳
I'll bring you a jacket.
我去拿外套給妳
AKIRA KUSANO
（草野彰）
Welcome home.
回來啦
I'm home.
我回來了
Were you drinking?
你喝酒了嗎？
When you get transferred, there are all kinds of things to do.
一旦被調職，就有各式各樣的歡送會
Farewell drinks with friends. Clink! Farewell!
跟朋友喝酒餞別，乾杯，再會
Friends
朋友
aren't something you can make just because you want to, are they?
不是想認識就能認識的，對吧？
You want to stay here?
你想待在這裡嗎？
What?
什麼？
You've only got a year left.
你只剩一年就畢業了
We could find you a boarding house. You would be fine.
可以幫你找個寄宿家庭 你不會有問題的
How come? Doing that for Shuji is unfair!
為什麼？只有哥能留下來太狡猾了
Yes, that's right.
就是說啊
And there are things you need me for, right?
你有很多事會需要我，對吧？
Like for housework.
像做家事之類的事
You really have suffered through a lot, haven't you?
你真的過得很辛苦，對吧？
First,
首先
think about what you want.
想想你自己想要的是什麼
Okay?
好嗎？
The people
真正…
who will feel the loneliest
感到最孤單的人
aren't us,
不是我們
but Shuji, right?
而是修二，對吧？
He's the type
他是那種…
who never shows that kind of thing, isn't he?
不會表現出來的人，對吧？
I want him to go cheerfully.
我希望他高高興興地轉學
I want to send him off with a smile.
我想笑著送他離開
You think we can?
我們做得到嗎？
We will.
可以的
Right.
沒錯
Arf!
汪
-What do you want us to do? -What?
-你要我們怎麼做？ -什麼？
-Arf! Arf!
-汪…
-There's nothing I want. -What do you want?
-我什麼都不想要 -你想要什麼？
Unless you say something, Nobuta won't give up.
除非你開口，否則野豬不會罷休的
Before you go, I want to do something that we will all remember.
在你轉學前 我想做一件值得紀念的事
-I really don't want anything like that. -I can think of something easily.
-真的不必了 -我隨便都能想到
Okay.
好吧
Like what?
那你想到什麼？
Like…
比方說…
have Nobuta become a shrine maiden.
讓野豬成為巫女
What? A shrine maiden?
什麼？巫女？
-Yes. -At a shrine?
-對 -神社的那種？
And then she'll give you the "Nobuta power charge!"
然後她要說“野豬能量，注入”
Nobuta as a shrine maiden?
野豬當巫女？
You know, that just might work.
好像挺不錯的
It totally would.
絕對超讚
Nobuta?
野豬？
-You're leaving? -Did you take that seriously?
-妳要走了？ -妳當真了嗎？
That was just a joke.
那只是在開玩笑
-You knew it was a joke, right? -Yes.
-你知道那是開玩笑的吧？ -我當然知道
Excuse me!
不好意思
Can I help you?
有什麼事嗎？
Well…
那個…
Why are you here?
你怎麼在這裡？
This is my family's home.
這是我家的房子
You're a Shinto priest?
你是神主嗎？
Yes!
是啊
My dad said that I could stay behind if I wanted to.
我爸說我可以留下來
Seriously? You wouldn't have to move?
真的嗎？這樣你就不用搬家了吧？
But I'm not so sure I should just do whatever I please.
但我不確定該不該照自己的想法做事
Don't be stupid!
別說傻話
Doing as you please is natural!
照自己的想法很正常啊
For any person,
對所有人來說
it's stupid not to do as you please!
不按照自己的想法做事最蠢了
Nobuta power charge!
野豬能量，注入
You really became one.
妳真的變成巫女了
Seriously?
妳當真了？
I'll do whatever you want.
你要我做什麼都可以
That's how much I appreciate what you've done, Shuji.
因為我非常感謝你，修二
I've got to go. I'm still on the clock.
我得走了，我還要打工
She's such a goofball.
她真是個傻瓜
She sure is.
對啊
Hey! Stop!
喂，站住
Help!
救命
Stop!
站住
-Get him! -Hey! Get him!
-抓住他 -喂，抓住他
Cut it out!
住手
-Shut up! -Cut it out!
-閉嘴 -住手
Cut it out!
住手
Am I dreaming?
我在做夢嗎？
Koji?
浩二？
Just talking in your sleep?
在說夢話嗎？
You're worried about moving?
你在擔心搬家的事嗎？
It will be all right.
不會有事的
Don't you worry.
別擔心
No, it's still yucky.
還是很難吃
-It is not yucky! -There it is! "Yuck!"
-才不難吃 -來了，“難吃”
Her "yuck" never gets old!
她的“難吃”永遠聽不膩
I wonder why it never gets old!
怎麼看都不會膩呢
Is that right?
是嗎？
Does it still hold memories for you?
這便當有你的回憶嗎？
You know what?
聽我說
I think I'm going to move.
我想我還是離開好了
Why?
為什麼？
I'm worried about my brother too.
我也很擔心我弟弟
I mean, when my dad doesn't come home from work until late,
再說，如果我爸加班
he'll have to eat all by himself.
他就得一個人吃飯了
Yes, that may be so, but
那倒也是，但是…
why don't you consider your own needs
你為什麼…
a little more?
不多看重自己一點呢？
Does doing things for other people
為別人付出
mean you're not considering your own needs?
就代表不看重自己嗎？
You know…
你知道嗎？
When I was working so hard doing things for Nobuta,
當我為了野豬而努力時
I felt I was really being myself.
是最像我自己的時候
That's how I felt.
我是這樣想的
Didn't you feel that way too?
你不也這麼覺得嗎？
SNOB
（勢利眼）
MORON
（笨蛋）
The same with Nobuta. When she's trying to make people happy,
野豬也一樣，當她想逗大家開心時
doesn't she seem the most alive to you?
你不覺得她看起來最有活力嗎？
Aren't you going to come to school?
妳不來學校嗎？
If I went to school, I might start bullying you again.
如果我去上學，可能又會欺負妳
That's okay. You can bully me.
沒關係，妳可以欺負我
I'll take all your bullying.
我願意接受妳的霸凌
I swear. I can take it.
我發誓，我承受得住
You sure are dumb, Kotani.
妳真傻，小谷
You really are.
真的好傻
So, please
所以…
come to school.
來上學吧
I'll think about it.
我會考慮的
MAY AOI RETURN TO SCHOOL
（希望蒼井回來上學）
MAY AKIRA HAVE LOTS OF FUN
（希望彰過得很開心）
MAY SHUJI BE FINE WHEREVER HE GOES
（希望修二不管到哪裡 都能過得很好）
Darn you!
可惡
Oh, dear!
糟了
It broke?
斷了嗎？
This is a pretty darn important tree.
這是一棵相當重要的樹
What will happen?
會發生什麼事呢？
You'll be cursed.
妳會遭天譴的
Cursed?
遭天譴？
And it won't be you who's cursed.
而且遭天譴的人不是妳
It'll happen to the person who's most precious to you.
而是妳最重要的人
I can't let that happen!
這樣可不行
Well, then give this to that person.
那就把這個交給那個人
Can I have one more?
可以再給我一個嗎？
Since it's for the person most precious to you, you only get one!
因為是最重要的人，所以只能有一個
Only one!
只有一個
While you're standing there,
妳站在這裡時
something may have already happened to that person.
那個人可能已經出事了
Hey! She threw it down!
居然亂丟
Darn it!
可惡
Oh, dear.
天啊
CHIZUKA SHRINE PROTECTION FROM EVIL
（千束神社，趨吉避凶）
-I saw them by the river. -The river?
-我在河邊看到他們 -河？
Shuji!
修二
Akira!
彰
What's wrong?
怎麼了？
It's nothing.
你們沒事？
What?
什麼？
Have you been cursed?
你們遭天譴了嗎？
-Cursed? What do you mean? -Yes.
-遭天譴？什麼意思？ -對啊
I broke a branch off a tree at the shrine.
我在神社弄斷了一根樹枝
He said the person most precious to me would be cursed.
我最重要的人會遭天譴
So he told me to give this to the person most precious to me.
所以神主叫我把這個 交給我最重要的人
Question.
我有問題
Who is the person most precious to you?
對妳來說最重要的人是誰？
But there's only one of those.
那東西只有一個耶
I only get one since only one person can be it.
因為最重要的人只能有一個
I can't choose.
我選不出來
Then give it to Akira.
-那就給彰吧 -等等
Hold on a second!
等一下
How come you're always taking the cool way out?
你怎麼老是愛耍帥？
You make me look like a coward who's afraid of some kind of curse.
你這樣讓我看起來 像個害怕遭天譴的膽小鬼
Fine. I'll take it.
好吧，那給我
Hold on!
等一下
If I really am the most precious person, I'll get brutally cursed.
如果我真的是最重要的人 就會遭天譴
Then which is it? You really are a pain, man. A real pain.
那到底要怎樣？你真的好討厭，真煩
-Then what will we do? -I'll get a saw.
-那我們該怎麼辦？ -我去拿鋸子
We don't have one.
我們沒鋸子
I've got one.
我剛好有帶
Here.
給妳
I'm always prepared.
我總是會做好準備
Wait! Hold on!
等等，等一下
What are you doing? Hold on! Stop!
妳在做什麼？等一下，住手
You'll be cursed if you do that.
這樣做會遭天譴的
But both of you are precious to me.
但你們兩個對我來說都很重要
Then you'll just have to cut it. Do it!
那只好切開了，動手吧
"Do it"? No! Don't do it! Stop! Let go of that!
“動手”？不，別動手，放開
That was close.
真是好險
Fine.
好吧
I'm sorry.
對不起
Let's all be cursed together.
我們一起遭天譴吧
Oh, dear!
可惡
I broke it.
我弄斷了
Who is the most precious person to me?
我最重要的人是誰？
Look closely.
仔細看
I am bleeding.
我流血了
No, you're not.
沒有啊
-I was cursed. -No, you weren't.
-遭天譴了 -才沒有
Whoa! What happened?
發生什麼事了？
I kind of fell down some stairs.
我摔下樓梯了
Seriously?
真的嗎？
But I'm just fine!
但我沒事啦
-I can stand up. See? -You okay?
-我能站起來，看吧？ -你還好嗎？
-You all right? -Yes, I'm okay.
-你沒事吧？ -我沒事
-You okay? -I'm just fine. See? I'm standing.
-你還好嗎？ -我沒事，看吧？我可以站起來
What happened?
怎麼了？
You must have been cursed!
你一定是遭天譴了
What?
什麼？
Hey! Out of the way!
借過
You okay?
你還好嗎？
Is the guy you like Shittaka?
妳喜歡的人是植木誠嗎？
-I fell down some stairs. -Really?
-我從樓梯上摔下來了 -真的嗎？
Gee, who knows?
天曉得？
You're saying there's a chance?
妳的意思是有可能？
Please give this form to your dad. Okay?
請把這個表格交給你爸爸，好嗎？
Okay.
好
You're moving away, Kiritani?
桐谷，你要轉學了？
Yes.
對
Thank you for all you've done.
謝謝各位老師的照顧
Thank you.
謝謝你們
You're moving away?
你要轉學？
Yes.
對
You're moving? I'll miss you.
轉學啊？我會想你的
Here.
來
A bean jam bun?
紅豆麵包？
Mariko…
真理子
Sorry.
抱歉
You okay?
沒事吧？
I'm…
我…
What?
什麼？
I'm going to be moving away.
我要轉學了
I thought I should at least tell you this myself.
我覺得至少要親自告訴妳
Bye.
再見
Everybody!
各位
Hey everybody!
同學們
Hey! Listen!
你們聽我說
-What is it? -Shuji's moving away!
-什麼事？ -修二要轉學了
-What? -Seriously?
-什麼？ -真的嗎？
Seriously!
不會吧
-No way! I had no idea. -When?
-不可能啊，我都沒聽說 -什麼時候？
After the semester.
這學期結束後
-Seriously? -That's not so far off!
-真的嗎？ -那就快了啊
Why hasn't he told us?
他為什麼沒告訴我們？
Yes! Why hasn't he told us?
對啊，他為什麼都沒說？
-How come? -Yes! How come?
-為什麼？ -對啊，為什麼？
Shuji!
修二
What? What is it?
什麼？怎麼了？
What is it?
怎麼了？
You're moving away?
你要轉學了？
Didn't I tell you guys?
我沒跟你們說嗎？
-No! You didn't! -Darn you!
-你沒說啊 -可惡
When are you moving?
你什麼時候要搬家？
In the new year.
明年初
-That's really soon! -Why didn't you tell us?
-那不就快了嗎？ -你怎麼沒告訴我們？
You should tell us!
你應該告訴我們的
You're such a fucking idiot! That's important shit you should tell us!
你真是個混蛋 這麼重要的事你應該告訴我們
It's been a while since Shuji was surrounded by people.
修二好久沒被大家圍繞了
Yes.
是啊
It's good.
很好
Did I ever confiscate anything from you?
你有東西被我沒收嗎？
No, I don't think so.
應該沒有
-And this isn't yours. -Right.
-這不是你的 -對
This either.
這個也不是
The bad thing about you is that you try to win every game you play.
你的缺點就是每個遊戲都想贏
So for you,
你覺得最厲害的…
this.
是這個
But remember, in some games, the two is the strongest.
但別忘了，在某些遊戲中 老二才是最強的
Only play where you can win.
所以用自己能取勝的遊戲 決勝負就行了
There. A present from me.
好，這就是送你的禮物
Wait.
等等
I think I said something pretty great just now.
我剛剛好像說了很勵志的話
Right?
-對啊 -對吧？
-Kiritani! -Yes?
-桐谷同學 -是？
This is a parting gift.
這是餞別禮
-What? Really? -Yes.
-什麼？真的嗎？ -對
Thank you.
謝謝
Wow! It's hand-knitted!
是手織的
Wow.
天啊
What? Why is there an "H" on it?
什麼？為什麼上面有H？
My initials are "K.S."
我名字的縮寫是KS
You're still young, so don't sweat the little things.
你這麼年輕，別計較這種小事
Wait! Did you break up or something?
等等，難道妳跟男友分手了？
I'll do my best too!
我也會加油的
She must have broken up.
看來是分手了
Hey.
對了
-Kiritani. -Yes?
-桐谷同學 -是？
I heard you're moving.
我聽說你要轉學了
Thank you for everything.
這段時間謝謝你的照顧
Okay then.
好吧
Use this for anything you'd like to eat.
用這個吃你喜歡的東西吧
Can I?
可以嗎？
It's just a lame joke.
只是個冷笑話
I'll be back quickly.
我馬上就回來
Wait!
等等
What? Why did you come home?
什麼？妳怎麼回來了？
-There it is! -What's wrong?
-找到了 -怎麼了？
I hid something I didn't want you to see!
我藏了不想讓你看到的東西
I was in Kathmandu when I suddenly remembered it!
我在加德滿都時突然想起來了
You should have called.
妳打電話回來說一聲就好啦
But then you'd see it.
但那樣你就會看到它
What's wrong with that? We're married.
那有什麼關係？我們都結婚了
Okay, I'm going back. Oh, yeah.
好，那我先走了，就這樣
When I come home next time, it will be our new place, right?
下次我回家時，就會是在新家了吧？
I need to make sure I don't forget that. Bye!
我得記住這點，再見
She's so sweet.
她好可愛
What?
什麼？
It says "Satoru Kiritani." That's you, Dad.
這上面寫著“桐谷悟”，是爸爸的
That's a letter I wrote to her when I was young.
那是我年輕時寫給她的信
-A letter from Dad. -Wait a minute!
-爸爸寫的信 -等一下
She returned from Kathmandu to get that?
她從加德滿都回來拿那個？
There are some memories you want to keep for yourself.
有些回憶只想要留給自己嘛
She didn't want to toss it or let anyone see it.
她不想丟掉，也不想讓別人看到
No way. You called her "Nobutan"?
不會吧？你叫她“小野豬”？
What?
什麼？
Who said you could look? Hey! Kid!
誰說你可以看的？喂，臭小子
Memories you want to keep for yourself?
想留給自己的回憶？
The end of semester ceremony will now begin.
現在開始進行結業式
Everyone,
各位同學
please assemble in the gym.
請到體育館集合
The end of semester ceremony will now begin.
現在開始進行結業式
Shuji, where's your jacket?
修二，你的外套呢？
-What? I forgot! You guys go on ahead. -Bye.
-什麼？我忘了，你們先走吧 -待會見
Oh, perfect timing!
來得正好
What's this?
這是什麼？
You can have those.
送給你們
These things…
這個東西
When you have two of them, they say you'll gain happiness.
聽說拿到兩個就會幸福喔
If these will bring happiness, then why don't you keep them?
如果它能帶來幸福 老師怎麼不自己留著？
You're sharing your happiness with us?
妳要跟我們分享妳的幸福？
Since you each get one, they're like seeds of happiness.
你們一人有一個 它就像是幸福的種子
The rest depends on your luck and effort to increase them and obtain happiness.
剩下的就要靠自己的努力和運氣 讓它茁壯，才能收穫幸福
Grow up into adults who can share that happiness with others.
希望你們能成為 將這份幸福分享給別人的大人
Good luck!
加油
I wonder what it is.
是什麼呢？
-I'll open it. -Go ahead.
-我要打開了 -開吧
I wonder what it is.
是什麼呢？
Wait…
等等
You mean,
結果…
each of us still ended up with just one?
我們最後還是一人一個嗎？
You know,
說真的
I've never really understood what it meant
我一直不知道喜歡一個人
to like someone.
是什麼意思
But thanks to Nobuta, I think I've figured it out.
但多虧了野豬，我想我懂了
Having a fun time eating stuff together.
一起開心地吃著東西
Seeing the same sight together
一起看著同樣的景色
and thinking, "I'll never forget this sight."
心裡想著“我永遠忘不了這一幕”
And laughing together until you drop.
一起笑到跌倒
And sometimes worrying about them.
有時候也會擔心對方
And thinking,
然後想著
"I sure wish I could spend more time with them."
“真希望我能多陪陪他們”
I realized that liking someone is really just those trivial things.
原來喜歡一個人，其實從那些 微不足道的小事就能感受到
From now on…
從現在起
whenever I start to like someone…
每當我喜歡上某人
I'll probably remember you, Nobuta.
我大概就會想起妳，野豬
It'll remind me that you're the one…
因為那種感覺提醒了我
who taught me all that.
是妳教會我這些事的
Kotani…
小谷
Thanks.
謝謝妳
It's the same with me.
我也有相同的想法
Thank you.
謝謝你
It pains me that this is all I can say.
我很難過我只能說這句話
I wish I could convey to you everything that I'm thinking.
真希望我能把我全部的想法都告訴你
I wish I could tell you
我希望能告訴你
just how much I appreciate what you've done.
我有多感激你做的一切
I understand.
我知道
you see, it's the same with me.
我也一樣
I feel like I need to tell Mariko this too.
我覺得我也必須告訴真理子 我心裡的話
Where will we go?
我們要去哪裡？
The beach.
海邊
The beach?
海邊？
Well, I kept saying we should go, but we never did.
我每次都說要去，但都沒有去
I didn't have much time.
我沒什麼時間準備
But imagine this is the beach.
妳就想像這是海邊吧
I thought it would be nice to have a bento lunch with you too.
我覺得在這裡 和妳一起吃便當應該會很棒
You made it?
那是你做的？
Yes.
對
This really does
這裡真的…
seem like the beach.
好像海邊
Are you cold?
妳會冷嗎？
Yes.
很冷啊
But this is fun.
但這樣很好玩啊
I'm so stupid.
我真笨
I had so much time to do this before.
以前明明有很多時間這麼做
If I had wanted to, I could have had so much more fun with you, Mariko.
要是我能說到做到 就可以跟妳有很棒的回憶
That's what you've been thinking?
你一直在想這些事？
I hope I'm a better person.
希望我已經成為更好的人
It's good.
好吃
Really? It is?
真的嗎？
Yes.
對啊
I'm sure I'll never forget
我一定不會忘記的
this food.
這一餐
This here, it's not as good as your broccoli dumplings, but I made this up.
這比不上妳的花椰菜燒賣 不過是我自創的
-What is it? -Zucchini and ground shrimp.
-是什麼？ -櫛瓜和蝦泥
Really?
真的嗎？
Kotani, thank you for earlier.
小谷，剛剛謝謝妳
We did that with…
我們是用…
The last thing I saw at school was
我在學校最後看到的是
Mariko and Nobuta having fun talking with each other.
真理子跟野豬聊得很開心的畫面
For some reason, that made me really, really happy.
不知道為什麼，那讓我感覺好幸福
Akira and I…
彰和我…
-Bye.
-再見
We said "bye" as if we'd meet tomorrow.
道別時，好像明天又會見面一樣
And neither of us looked back.
我們都沒有回頭
Oh, no!
糟糕
Mr. Saotome! That's the wrong character!
早乙女老師，這個字寫錯了
-What? -This.
-什麼？ -這個
Oh, no! It says "Dotani"!
不好了，寫成“胴谷”了
You've got to be kidding me! What are we going to do now?
不會吧？我們現在該怎麼辦？
I'm sorry!
對不起
Kiritani's departure isn't tomorrow. It's today!
桐谷不是明天出發，是今天
Today? You mean he's already left?
今天？所以他已經離開了嗎？
Yes. He's probably about to leave.
對，他大概要啟程了
Then we won't be in time!
那我們就來不及了
-Thank goodness! -What?
-太好了 -什麼？
No, I didn't mean that.
不，我不是那個意思
Come on. Aren't you going to see him off?
起來吧，你不去送他嗎？
I don't want to go.
我不想去
Just because it's painful doesn't mean you should run away.
你不能因為難過就逃避現實啊
Are you going to act like you never even knew Shuji?
你要裝作不認識修二嗎？
Are you?
是嗎？
Discarding the painful stuff means
拋棄痛苦的時光
you're discarding all the fun times too.
等於把開心的時光也丟掉了
You want that?
你想要那樣嗎？
I can't act like…
我不能假裝
those things never happened.
那些事從沒發生過
Then see things out to the very end.
那你就應該堅持到最後啊
Okay?
好嗎？
Hey.
好了
We're going.
我們要走了
-Okay.
-好
-We'll be going, Shuji.
-我們先上車了，哥
Hello?
喂？
Hello? Look left!
喂？看左邊
Shuji! Over here!
修二，看這裡
Look over here!
看這裡
Look left! Look left!
看左邊…
Shuji!
修二
Excuse me. Can you stop for a minute?
不好意思，可以停車一下嗎？
Damn you! We'll miss you!
混蛋，我們會想你的
-You came? -Yes! We're here!
-你們都來了？ -對啊，我們都來了
We're here, Shuji!
修二，我們來了
Okay. All right!
好，那麼
Let's all take photos together!
大家一起拍照吧
Ready. Go.
一、二
-Ready. Go. Bitchin'!
-一、二，帥啦
Ready, go. The squares.
一、二，要乖喔
-Double your power!
-雙倍力量
Say "kimchi"!
西瓜甜不甜
-Yip!
-嗷
Smile, handsome dudes!
帥哥們，笑一個
Say "rhinoceros beetle."
說“獨角仙”
-Yip!
-嗷
Gather together, everyone!
大家靠在一起
-Get closer! -Why are you putting your eye up to it?
-靠近一點… -你幹嘛把眼睛湊上去？
You can see it from here!
從這裡就看得到
Here goes!
要拍囉
-Is this… -Destiny?
這一定是…
Thank you so much.
非常謝謝大家
Bicycle!
腳踏車
-Bicycle!
-腳踏車
Shuji!
修二
Nobuta power charge!
野豬能量，注入
Everything in this world is a game.
世間的一切都只是一場遊戲
Anyone who thinks they've lost and gives up midway is a fool.
以為輸了就半途而廢的人，就是笨蛋
AMIGO HIGH SCHOOL
（網五高中）
Sorry.
抱歉
I'm kind of nervous.
我有點緊張
Those who survive to the end
那些生存到最後
and enjoy the game to the fullest are the winners.
並盡情享受遊戲的人才是贏家
That's probably how the rules work in this world.
這或許就是這世上的生存之道吧
No matter what happens now,
以後不管發生什麼事
this new Shuji Kiritani won't fall into despair.
這個嶄新的桐谷修二絕不會陷入絕望
If you don't sit down in the next three seconds,
如果三秒內不坐下
you'll be in real trouble. Do you want that?
你們就倒大楣了，你們想要這樣嗎？
Shuji Kiritani has moved here from Tokyo.
桐谷修二是從東京轉學過來的
I'm Shuji Kiritani.
我叫桐谷修二
It's nice to meet you.
請大家多多關照
Am I hallucinating?
是幻覺嗎？
What's wrong?
怎麼了？
I'm just kinda nervous.
我只是有點緊張
Oh, okay.
好的
Applause!
鼓掌
No way!
不會吧
I've fallen into despair.
我已經絕望了
-Yo!
-喲
Hi.
嗨
Say, when did Kusano move here?
草野是什麼時候轉來的？
-Yesterday! -It was really amazing.
-昨天 -他超酷的
He landed on the playground in a helicopter. Like George Bush.
他搭直升機降落在操場上 像喬治布希一樣
-Yes! Like Bush! -That's a good one!
-對，像布希一樣 -說得好
Damn! That hurts!
可惡，好痛
Yamazaki and Umigame are going at it!
山崎和海龜打起來了
Where?
在哪裡？
The gym!
體育館
Seriously?
-真的嗎？
What?
什麼？
It's really bad! Come on!
場面真的很糟，快點
-You need to handle this, Shuji! -Wait!
-修二，你得來處理才行 -等等
-It's bad! -Who's Yamazaki and Umigame?
-很糟糕 -山崎和海龜是誰？
-Wait. Wait a second. -What?
-等等，等一下 -什麼？
Am I smiling?
我在笑嗎？
Yes.
對啊
You're smiling.
妳笑了
See?
妳看
Oh, yeah.
對了
Neither of them is here anymore.
他們兩個都已經不在了
"One must comprehend times such as these."
“必須理解這樣的時代”
So the verb "nari" here is the predicate form of the auxiliary verb "nari."
這裡的助動詞是表示斷定語氣
That's because the connecting "beki" is the attributive form of the auxiliary.
因為前面的詞是助動詞的連體形
Why the heck did you move here?
你到底為什麼要轉學來這裡？
Now Nobuta's all alone again.
現在野豬又一個人了
Nobuta's the one who said,
是野豬說
"Shuji and Akira are two peas in a pod."
“修二與彰是一體的”
She said, "I'll be fine alone."
她說“我自己一個人沒關係的”
Is she really going to be okay alone?
她一個人真的沒問題嗎？
She said, "I'll cry for the first three days, but I swear I'll get over it."
她說“前三天我會哭 但我發誓我會克服的”
Nobuta said that?
野豬那樣說？
Yes.
對
I see.
這樣啊
You know what? Way over across this sky,
你知道嗎？這片天空的另一端
Nobuta is there.
野豬就在那裡
Hey! Doesn't that cloud look like it's smiling?
你不覺得那朵雲好像在笑嗎？
-It does? -Yes! That one!
-是嗎？ -對，那朵雲啊
I'm
我…
able to smile now.
現在會笑了
I'm able to…
我可以…
smile properly now!
真心笑出來了
Us guys…
我們三個…
Yes?
什麼？
I think we can survive pretty much anywhere.
我想我們在哪裡都能生存吧
Bam!
砰
She can't hear you.
她聽不到你說的話
She'll wonder.
她會想聽到的
We can survive anywhere.
我們在哪裡都能生存下去的
THIS DRAMA IS A WORK OF FICTION
（本劇純屬虛構）
Subtitle translation by: Brian Athey
字幕翻譯：黃雅婷